<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse about edification in answer to a question, whether it is lawful for any man to forsake the communion of the Church of England, and go to the separate meetings, because he can better edifie there?</title>
            <author>Hascard, Gregory.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43054</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1108</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4350</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12895526</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12895526</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95169</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43054)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95169)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 919:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse about edification in answer to a question, whether it is lawful for any man to forsake the communion of the Church of England, and go to the separate meetings, because he can better edifie there?</title>
                  <author>Hascard, Gregory.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills, Jun. for Fincham Gardiner ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Gregory Hascard.  Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95169:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE ABOUT Edification: IN ANSWER TO A QUESTION, Whether it is Lawful for any Man to forſake the Communion of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and go to the <hi>Separate Meetings,</hi> becauſe he can better Edifie there?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Jun. for <hi>Fincham Gardiner</hi> at the <hi>White Horſe</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:95169:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95169:2"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE About EDIFICATION:</head>
            <p>In Anſwer to a <hi>Queſtion,</hi>
               <lb/> WHether it is lawful for any Man to forſake the Communion of the Church of <hi>England, </hi> and go to the ſeparate Meetings, becauſe he can better Edifie there?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> It is Unlawful.</p>
            <p>To make this plain, two things muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> What ſort of Perſon this is, who asks this Queſtion.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> What he means by Edification.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:95169:3"/>
            <p> As to the Perſon, he is ſuppos'd to be one, that is fully ſatisfi'd, that he may lawfully Communicate with the Church of <hi>England;</hi> That there are no Terms of Communion put upon him, but which he can comply withal with a good Conſcience; That there is nothing in it contrary to the Word of God, natural Reaſon, or plain Conſequences fetcht from both or either. And therefore he who thinks, that there are ſome things unlawful in the Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is not concern'd in the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; for he ſeparates upon the Account of Unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and not Edification only, as is ſuppos'd in the Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By Edification is meant, an Improvement of his Spiritual Condition in the full latitude wherein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it may truly conſiſt, whether in the Articles of his Faith, which in the ſeparate Congregations are better taught, more clearly prov'd, more fitly appli'd to his practice, and to ſupport his hopes of Heaven, or whether in the Rules of Life, which are there more exactly laid down, and more ſtrongly enforc'd upon his Mind, or in Prayers, which among them are better compos'd, and more fervently ſent up unto God, and in all other parts of Devotion, which there are better fram'd and order'd to affect his Soul, and make a truly Chriſtian man.</p>
            <p>Theſe two things being explain'd, and premis'd, the Anſwer to the Queſtion will be found true, if we conſider theſe following Reaſons:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Ground upon which the Queſtion ſtands is falſe, <hi>viz.</hi> There is not better Edification to be had in the ſeperate Meetings, than in the Communion of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This will appear, if we conſider,
<list>
                  <item>1. How apt and fit the whole Conſtitution of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95169:3"/>Church of <hi>England</hi> is to Edifie Mens Souls.</item>
                  <item>2. That this Conſtitution is well us'd, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag'd, by the Paſtors of our Church for Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt will be manifeſt by induction, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſeveral parts of her Conſtitution reducible to theſe following Heads:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Her Creeds or Articles of Faith are thoſe which our Diſſenters themſelves allow; which are full and plain, containing all Neceſſaries and Fundamentals in Religion, nothing defective in Vitals or Integrals to make up the Body of a true Chriſtian Church. Chriſt that founded his Church, beſt knew what was abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to her being, and there is nothing that he hath declar'd to be ſo, but is contain'd in her Creeds. Whatever is fundamental for us to know of the Nature of God, is to be found there, or by eaſie Conſequences deduced from them. Would we know what we ought to believe of the Nature of Chriſt or his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, the Deſigns of his coming upon Earth, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of his Reign and Government, the Rewards and Puniſhments of his Laws, the Times of Account and Retribution, the mighty Miracles and extraordinary Acts of Providence to confirm theſe, we may read them at large in Holy Writ, and find wiſely ſumm'd up in our Creeds. Whoſe Articles, to help the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories of Men, are ſhort and few; and to aſſiſt the dulneſs of their Underſtandings, are manifeſt and plain; they containing no more, than what was ſome way or other, either ſuppos'd before, or included in, or following from that brief Creed, <hi>the Character of a true Chriſtian,</hi> that <hi>Jeſus is the Chriſt, the Son of God.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 John 4.15.5.5.</note> Whatever is any way reveal'd by God as neceſſary, is an Article of our Faith; nothing that is nice and obſcure, fit only for diſpute and wrangling, is brought
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95169:4"/>into our Creed; all whoſe Articles are Primitive and of Divine right, none of them purely ſpeculative or curious, but plain and uſeful in order to practice, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally leading to an Holy Life, the end of all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. We love every thing that is truly ancient, and Apoſtolical; but we cannot call that an eternal truth, which was but yeſterday, and we are ready to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace all truth, but we cannot call that the High Prieſt which is but the Fringe of his Garment. We believe all that the early Chriſtians in the firſt 300 Years thought ſufficient for them to know (and they were very ſecure that this would ſave them.) And if any truth be diſguis'd or defac'd by the iniquity of the deſcending Ages, we are ready to receive it, whenever it is made clear, and reſtor'd to its former ſhape and complexion; we caſting out obſtinacy and perverſneſs out of our Practice, as well as niceneſs out of our Creed. That Creed that Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught, the Saints, Martyrs, and Confeſſors, the Wife and Good Men in the firſt and pureſt days of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity believ'd, and were ſecure of Heaven by it, and therefore added no more; that Faith this Church maintains, which will ſufficiently and effectually Edifie the Souls of Men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Neceſſity ſhe lays upon a Good Life and Works. For this is the ſolemn intention of all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, our Creed, our Prayers, our Sacraments, and Diſcipline, and all Devotion. Her Creed is ſuch, that all its Articles ſo directly, or by natural conſequence, lead unto Virtue and Holineſs, that no man can firmly believe them, but they muſt ordinarily influence his Manners, and better his Converſation; and if by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his Creed his Life is not mended, he either ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly and groſly miſtakes their Conſequences, or is wilfully deſperate. Our Church publickly declares,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95169:4"/>that without preparatory Virtues, no Acts of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, however ſet off with Zeal and Paſſion, are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing unto God, and if obedience be wanting afterwards, are but ſcene and ſhow. Such a Faith ſhe lays down as fundamental to ſalvation, which reſts not in the brain and ſtory, in magnifying and praiſing, in ſighing and repeating, but in the production of Mercy, Charity, and Juſtice, and ſuch excellent Vertues. She makes no debates between Faith and Good Works, nor argues nicely about the preference, nor diſputes critically the Mode how joyntly they become the condition of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but plainly determins, that without Faith and Good Works, no Man ſhall ſee God. She not only keeps to a Form of ſound Words, but to a Converſation of equal Firmneſs and Solidity. Her Feſtivals are to commemorate the Virtues of Excellent Men, and to recommend them as Preſidents for imitation. Her Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, which were principally deſign'd for Decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, may alſo remind us of thoſe Virtues which become the <hi>Worſhippers of God.</hi> Her Collects and Petitions are for Grace to ſubdue our Follies, and to fortifie our reſolutions for Holineſs. Her Diſcipline is to laſh the ſturdy into Sobriety and Goodneſs: And her Homilies are plainly and ſmartly, to declare againſt the groſs Acts of Impiety, and to perſwade a true Chriſtian De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment in Word and Deed, and her whole Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aims at the Deſign of the Goſpel, to teach Men to live <hi>Soberly, Righteouſly, and Godly.</hi> She flatters and lulls no Man aſleep in Vice, but tells all ſecure ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners plainly, that they do not pray nor receive aright, that they are not abſolv'd, that their perſons are not juſtified, nor can have any true hopes of Heaven, except they purifie themſelves, and be really juſt and good. She neither uſeth nor allows any nice diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in plain Duties to baffle our Obedience, nor
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95169:5"/>ſuffers a cunning head to ſerve the deſigns of a wicked heart, and teach Men learnedly to ſin; but urgeth plain Virtues laid down diſtinctly in holy Writ, and taught by Natural Reaſon and Conſcience (without calling them mean Duties or ordinary Morality) to be the great Ornament of our Religion, and the Soul of our Faith. She ſets no abſtruſe and phantaſtick Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, nor any Marks, whoſe truth muſt be fetcht in by long deductions and conſequences for Men to judge by, whether they ſhall be ſav'd or no, but Faith and good Works, which the Philoſopher and meaneſt Chriſtian can eaſily judge of the civil intereſt of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is Edifi'd by ſuch a Church, preſſing the neceſſity of good Works, not only thereby enforcing Peace and Juſtice, Pity and Tenderneſs, Humility and Kindneſs, one towards another; but ſhe makes Kings ſafer, and Subjects more ſecure, condemning both Tyranny and Diſobedience; Parents more obey'd, and Subjects more lov'd, commanding equally Bowels and Affections, and Duty and Honour; Maſters and Servants, Husbands and Wives, and all Relations are kept in their juſt Bounds and Priviledges. With other Churches we make good Works neceſſary to Salvation, but think our ſelves more modeſt and ſecure in taking away Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance and Merit, and advancing the Grace of Chriſt: With other Men we cry up Faith, but not an hungry and a ſtarved one, but what is fruitful of good Works, and ſo have all that others contend for, with greater modeſty and ſecurity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How fitly this Church is conſtituted to excite true Devotion. When we make our Addreſſes unto God, we ought to have worthy and reverend Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Nature, a true ſenſe and plain knowledge of the Duty, and of the Wants and Neceſſities, for which we pray to be ſuppli'd. All which our Church,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95169:5"/>to help our Devotion, plainly ſets down, deſcribing God by all his Attributes of juſt, wiſe, and laying forth the Vices and Infirmities of Humane Nature, and that none elſe but God can cure our needs. When her Sons are to pray, the matter of her Petitions are not nice and controverted, trivial, or words of a Party, but plain and ſubſtantial, wherein all agree. Her Words in Prayer are neither ruſtick nor gay, the whole Compoſure neither too tedious nor too ſhort, decently order'd to help our Memories, and wandring Thoughts. Reſponſals and ſhort Collects in Publick Devotion are ſo far from being her fault, that they are her beauty and prudence. There are few Caſes and Conditions of Humane Life, whether of a Civil or Spiritual nature, which have not their proper Prayers and particular Petitions for them, at leaſt as is proper for publick Devotions. When we return our Thanks, we have proper Offices to enflame our Paſſions, to quicken our Reſentment, to excite our Love, and to confirm our future Obedience, the beſt inſtance of gratitude. When we Commemorate the Paſſion of Chriſt, we have a Service fit to move our Affections, to aſſiſt our Faith, to enlarge our Charity, to ſhew forth and exhibit Chriſt and all his bloody Sufferings, every way to qualifie us, to diſcharge that great Duty. She hath indeed nothing to kindle an Enthuſiaſtick heat, nor any thing that ſavours of Raptures and Extaſies, which commonly flow from temper or fraud, but that which makes us manly devout, our judgment ſtill guiding our affections. When we enter firſt into Religion, and go out of the World, we have two proper Offices, Baptiſm, and Burial, full of Devotion to attend thoſe purpoſes: ſo that if any doth not pray, and give thanks, communicate, and live like a Chriſtian; 'tis not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Services to promote theſe are too plain, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95169:6"/>hungry, beggarly and mean, but their own mind is not fitly qualifi'd before they uſed them; bring but an honeſt mind to theſe parts of Devotion, a true ſenſe of God, ſober and good purpoſes, and affections well diſpos'd, that which is plain will prove Seraphical, improve our Judgment, heighten our Paſſions, and make the Church a Quire of Angels. Without which good diſpoſition our Devotion is but conſtitution or melancholy peeviſhneſs, fullenneſs, or Devotion to a Party, a Sacrifice that God will not accept.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Her Order and Diſcipline. Such are the Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities and Manners of Men, not to be taught only by naked Virtue, a natural Judgment, or an immediate Teaching of God; but by Miniſtry and Diſcipline, decent Ceremonies and Conſtitutions, and other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Methods: theſe are the outward Pales and Guards, the Supplies and Helps for the Weakneſs of Humane Nature. Our Church hath fitted and ordered theſe ſo well, as neither to want or to abound; not to make Religion too gay, nor leave her ſlovingly, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rude nor phantaſtick, but is cloth'd in dreſſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to a manly Religion, not to pleaſe or gratifie our ſenſes, ſo as to fix there, but to ſerve the reaſon and judgment of our Mind. There are none of our Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies which good Men, and wiſe Men, have not judged decent and ſerviceable to the great ends of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and none of them but derive themſelves from a very ancient Family, being us'd in moſt Ages, and moſt of the Churches of God, and have decency, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, and uſefulneſs, to plead for them, to help our Memories, to excite our Affections, to render our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices orderly and comely. Were we indeed all Soul, and ſuch ſeraphical Saints, and grown Men, as we make our ſelves, we might then plead againſt ſuch external helps, but when we have Natures of weakneſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95169:6"/>and paſſion, theſe outward helps may be call'd very convenient, if not generally neceſſary; and as our Nature is mixt of Soul and Body, ſo muſt always our Devotion be here, and ſuch God expects and is pleas'd with. Our Church is neither defective in Power and Diſcipline (had ſhe her juſt dues, and others would do well to joyn with her in her wiſhes, that they might be reſtor'd) which would turn all into confuſion; not yet tyrannical, want of authority breeding as many, if not more Miſeries than Tyranny, or too much Power, both of them ſevere Curſes of a Nation. But her Government, like her Clime, is ſo well tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd together, that the Members of this Chriſtian Society may not be diſſolute or rude with her, nor her Rulers inſolent; being conſtituted in the Church with their different Names and Titles, not for luſtre and greatneſs, and Secular purpoſes, but for ſuppreſſion of Vice, the maintaining of Faith, Peace, Order, and all Virtues, the true Edification of Mens Souls. And if thoſe Vices are not reprov'd and chaſtiz'd, which fall under her cognizance, 'tis not the fault of her Power, but becauſe by other ways ill reſtrain'd, unneceſſary Diviſions from her hindring der Diſcipline upon Offenders, and ſo they hinder that Edification which they contend for. This Government is not Modern, Particular, or purely Humane, but Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical, Primitive, and Univerſal, to time as well as place: till ſome private Perſons, for Number, Learning, or Piety, not to be equall'd to the good Men of old, who defended it, and obey'd it, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd for it, out of ſome miſtakes of humane frailty and paſſion, or born down with the iniquities of the times, began to change it, and declaim againſt it, though ſo very fit and proper to promote Chriſtanity in the World. This is a general account of that Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95169:7"/>that is to be had in that Church in which we live; a more particular one would be too long for this Diſcourſe; but thus much muſt be ſaid, that examin all her particular Parts, and Offices, you will find none of them light, or ſuperſtitious, novel, or too nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, ill diſpos'd, or uncouth, improper or burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, no juſt cauſe for any to revolt from her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion: but conſidering the preſent circumſtances of Chriſtianity, and Men, the beſt <hi>conſtituted Church in the World.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6.1.2 Pet. 3.18. Rom. 15.2.1 Cor. 14.3.</note> 
               <hi>If therefore Edification be going on to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, or growing in Grace, if it is doing good to the Souls of Men, if it be to make plain the great things in Religion to the underſtandings of Men,</hi> or whatever the import of it is, in relation to Faith or Virtue, which is the condition of our Salvation, it is to be found in this Church; whoſe Conſtitution is apt and fit to do all this: And St. <hi>Jude</hi> ſeems to tell us, that true Edification was a ſtranger to thoſe who ſeparated from the common building, <note place="margin">Verſ. 19.</note> but <hi>thoſe who kept to the Communion of the</hi> Church, <hi>built up themſelves in their moſt holy Faith, and pray'd in the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And the honeſt Chriſtian, with greater aſſurance, may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the Grace and Bleſſings of Chriſt, and the Divine Spirit, whoſe Promiſes are made to them, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the Communion of the Church, and not to them who divide from the Body, and have greater hopes of Edification from their Teacher, than the Grace of God, from <hi>Apollos,</hi> that waters, than from Chriſt, the chief Husbandman, who gives the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Conſtitution is us'd and manag'd in the beſt way, by the Paſtours of our Church to Edifie the Souls of Men. This will appear, if we conſider theſe two things:
<list>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:95169:7"/>
                  <item>1. That there are ſtrict Commands under great Panalties laid upon the Paſtours of our Church to do this; who are not left to their own freedom, and private judgment, or the ſorce only of common Chriſtianity upon them thus to improve Mens Souls committed to their charge, but have Temporal Mulcts and Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures held over them, to keep them to their Duty. That when they do inform or direct their Flocks about their Blief, they ſhould keep to the Analogy of Faith, or Form of ſound Words. Or when they perſwade to Practice, their Rules and Propoſitions muſt be according to Godlineſs. That whenever they Exhort or Rebuke, Preach or Pray, whenever they Direct, or Anſwer the Scruples of Mens Minds, in the whole Execriſe and Compaſs of their Miniſtry, they are to have an eye to the Creed, to regard Mercy and Juſtice, the Standard of good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; in ſhort, to preſerve Faith and a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience with ſubſtantial Devotion, which will to the purpoſe Edifie Mens Souls, and effectually ſave them.</item>
                  <item>2. That theſe Commands are obey'd by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours of our Church, and they do all things in it to Edification. For the truth of this, we appeal to good Men, and wiſe Men, in the Communion of our Church, who have Honeſty and Judgment to confeſs this truth, and with gratitude acknowledge, that the Paſtours of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have led them into the ways of Truth and Righteouſneſs, cured their Ignorance, and reform'd their Lives, and upon good grounds given them an aſſurance of Heaven. To ſay ſuch as theſe are prejudic'd, and want ſincerity and knowledge to paſs a judgment, is only to prove, what we juſtly ſuſpect, that they want true Edification among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſhould be better taught the Doctrine of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95169:8"/>Charity. Our <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Neighbours, impartial Judges, will give their Teſtimony to this Truth, who have own'd and commended the Government of this Church, condemn'd the Separation, magnifi'd the Prudence, Piety, and Works of her Governours, and Paſtours, and wiſh'd, that they and their Charge were under ſuch a Diſcipline, and tranſlated many of their Pious and Learned Works to Edifie and Save their People. <note place="margin">The Unreaſon-ableneſs of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, <hi>p.</hi> 117</note> Our diſſenting Brethren themſelves (at leaſt in the good Mood, and out of the heat of Diſpute) give their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to this, that the Inſtructions and Diſcourſes of our Paſtours from their Pulpits are Solid, Learned, Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate, and Pious, and their only Crime was, that ſometimes they were too well ſtudied, and too good. If in the great number of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy, ſome few may be lazy, one particular perſon may clothe his Doctrine in too gay a dreſs, another talks Scholaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally above the capacity of his hearers, a third too dully, a fourth too nicely, and opinionatively, and here and there a Paſtour anſwers not the true deſign of Preaching to inform Mens Minds, to guide their Conſciences, and move their Affections; what is this to the general Charge, that no Edification ſo good is to be had as in the ſeparate Meetings, the pretended Cauſe of their Separation; for 'tis no more a true Cauſe, than want of Accommodation or Room in Churches, for ſome to ſeparate, where good Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Conveniency too may be eaſily had. And ſince they compel our Paſtours to ſpeak well of themſelves by their detraction and ſpeaking ill of them, they muſt gladly <hi>ſuffer them as fools,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Cor. 11.19.</note> boldly to ſay, That ſince the Reformation, and many hundred years before, there hath not been a Clergy, ſo learned and pious, ſo prudent and painful, and every way induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to Edifie and ſave the Souls of Men, as now is in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:95169:8"/>
            <p> The Second Argument to confirm the Anſwer is, That thoſe that uſually make this pretence for Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, do commonly miſtake better Edification. We have prov'd already, that good and ſufficient Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, to ſave the Souls of Men, is to be had in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church. For if teaching plainly the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Faith, and laying down clearly Rules of Manners, uſing well compoſed Prayers, and proper Adminiſtration of Sacraments, be not good, and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Edification, I know not what Edification means: it may be heating of fancy, ſtirring up of humours, this, or that, and Men may as well define the thing they call Wit, as what Edification means. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to deſert the plain and great Duty of our Church Communion, for diſputable, doubtful, or truly miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Edification, is to be guilty of the ſin of Schiſm. In moſt caſes to judge what is better or beſt, is very hard, and requires a ſincere and conſidering head; and ſo it is in the buſineſs of better Edification, which is ſo eaſily miſtaken, eſpecially by the generality of the People, who are uſually ignorant of ſuch nice things, and prejudic'd by their Parties, and Affections, and are <hi>mutable and various, according to their fancies. For better Edification, purer Adminiſtrations, and Churches, and things that are more excellent, abſolute Prefection, and a leſs defective Way of Worſhip,</hi> are hard to underſtand, perplex mens minds, and fill them with innumerable doubts and ſcruples, and put them upon refining and purging ſo long, till they weaken and deſtroy the Spirit of Religion. And ſo they run themſelves into a known ſin, for dark and diſputable advantages; which indeed are only miſtakes, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally are theſe three that follow:
<list>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:95169:9"/>
                  <item>1. In taking nice and ſpeculative Notions for great and Edifying Truths. When Doctrins have been rais'd, only to pleaſe the temper of the curious and inquiſitive, yet have made many think, their hearts were warm'd, when their heads and fancies were gratifi'd. And dark and obſcure Diſcourſes about Angels, the ſtate of ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Souls, <note place="margin">Coloſ, 2. 18.</note> and things of the like nature, have made ſome call the Preacher high and myſterious, while others, teaching the way of Salvation plainly, by Faith and a good Converſation, have been leſſen'd, with the character of dull, honeſt, and moral Men, fit only for Catechiſts, and Chriſtians of the loweſt Form. Tickle but their imaginations with conjectural Diſcourſes about the ſituation of Paradiſe of old, or Hell now, and you are a ſounder Divine, than he, that only draws wholſom Concluſions from <hi>Adam</hi>'s preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rication, to caution you againſt ſin of the like nature, or how to avoid thoſe diſmal flames where ever they are. And others have been ſilly and phantaſtick in admiring thoſe who have pratled about the length of the Sword that guarded Paradiſe, or how the Spirits above paſs Eternity away, and ſcorn'd him, who in plain methods chalkt them out the way that will lead them to Heaven. <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.4.</note> The ancient <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> becauſe they made a mixture of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Fables, and Genealo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, of their <hi>Lilith</hi> and <hi>Behemoth,</hi> and fetcht in the ſtories of the Gods, out of <hi>Orpheus</hi> and <hi>Philiſtion,</hi> (two great Divines in the <hi>Pagan</hi> Religion) into plain Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, thought themſelves the moſt knowing Men, of the Secrets of God and Heaven, and wondred how only Faith upon Jeſus, and keeping of the Commands, could be knowing of God, or Wiſdom from above. The wranglings of the Schools, with their fine di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions and barbarous terms, ſitter for Magick than Chriſtianity, by their Diſciples have been priz'd for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95169:9"/>great and precious Truths. And Enthuſiaſtick Raptures, and flights, making once the Brain to ſwim, have ſnatcht the hearers beyond themſelves, and then thought them the Dictates of the Spirit, and the Teachings of God, and the more dark and obſcure the Doctrine hath been, the greater illumination it was eſteem'd, and call'd a noon-day Thought, which was a mid-night Dream. Such things as theſe paſs with too many for ſaving Truths, a great part of Mankind being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in their Heads, and corrupt in their Practice, eſpous'd to Parties and Intereſts, having Conſtitutions and Paſſions fit for theſe, they readily ſwallow them down. The Apoſtle <hi>confirms the truth of this,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>telling us the time will come, when they will not endure ſound Doctrine, but after their own luſts, ſhall they heap to themſelves Teachers, having itching ears,</hi> caus'd by ſome diſeaſe of Vice within, which is not to be cured by good Phyſick, but only ſcratched and gratifi'd; and and if the Food, though wholſom and good, be not to their Pallate and Fancy, they complain of hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and ſtarving. Theſe and many more are the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of a weak and ſickly nature, craving only nice and curious things for Spiritual Meat, and kecking at the ſincere Milk of the Word, plain and ſubſtantial Truths that it may grow thereby. To give therefore a liberty to every Man to run from an eſtabliſh'd Church, upon the account of better Edification, which is ſo often and eaſily miſtaken, is to direct Men into temptation and a ſnare, and is dangerous and ſinful; and when once the gap is open, where will, eſpecially the Vulgar ſtop? May we not add, that this pretence of better Edification is very ſit to diſguiſe and colour other Vices. When Controverſies have unhappily riſen, from an unjuſt denial of the Miniſters Rights and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95169:10"/>Dues, or the accidents of civil converſation, they make The Miniſtry, that was ſpiritual and good before, to be call'd dull and mean, and better muſt be ſought elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, while only Revenge or Covetouſneſs is at the bottom. Wandring Reports, or their own laviſh Tongue, and cenſorious Temper, have call'd ſome Paſtours, Covetous, or Intemperate, or branded them with other Vices, and then cry out, they cannot Edifie in ſuch a Church, and ſo make one fault help out another, and Defamation muſt excuſe their Schiſm.</item>
                  <item>2. In taking the Opinions of Parties for undoubted Truths eſſential to ſalvation. When men have once wedded a Party, and the Opinions peculiar to it, they magnifie and propagate them, grow ſurious for their defence, and call them the beſt part of Religion: and if theſe be not abetted and cry'd up by the Paſtours of our Church, or they differ from them in explications and diſtinctions of them, the way of ſalvation is not taught, they do not improve their Spiritual condition, and therefore is a juſt cauſe of their ſeparation. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Notion or Explication of Faith, and Spirit, Church, and Grace, Juſtification, Regeneration, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, Adoption, and other things of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are generally different in our Church from thoſe of the ſeparation, they therefore cry we deſtroy the ſaving Truths of the Goſpel, and inſtead of being Edifi'd, they find themſelves weakened in their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith. Though 'tis plain to all impartial judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that <hi>their ſenſe and interpretation</hi> of them, by natural conſequences leſſen the Grace of the Goſpel, and give ſecurity to lazy ſinners, a ſtrange ſort of Edification. For though our Charity is not ſo narrow, as to think every man a vicious perſon, who is thus miſtaken in his concluſions, yet however, this alters
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95169:10"/>not the nature of theſe Opinions, and their conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, and who knows how far men of ill Principles do improve them? Such is the perverſe and angry temper of many about their own Opinions, no way neceſſary to ſalvation, wherein wiſe men and good men may differ, which are not ſtated by Authority, and may not be determin'd till <hi>Elias</hi> come; yet if theſe be not inſiſted on, and preſs'd with vehemency, the great things of the Goſpel are omitted, and truths are wanting to their perfection. And if once the People are poſſeſs'd with Opinions and Notions, they grow fierce about them, and call them ſalvation truths, and run head-long into a Sea of diſorder; and tumult, for their defence. The Diſciples of the fifth Monarchy, the Pretenders to the Spirit, the Enemies of Childrends Baptiſm, think themſelves wrong'd, and the Goſpel hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, if caſually they hear you making Interpretations of the Kingdom of Jeſus, the Operations of the Spirit, and that divine inſtitution, different from their lewd ſenſe. And many Queſtions, when determin'd, after a great deal of labour, and paſſion, and expence of time, may improve our knowledge, but not Faith and a good Life, the only Edification. The early and beſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians thought themſelves mighty Saints, and ſecure of Heaven, if they only knew <hi>Jeſus and the Reſurrection</hi> in their full extent, and the World being ſuch ill Judges about any other Edification, it would be well if they return'd to this good old way, and reſt ſatiſi'd there, leſt they take the Inventions of Men, Rhetorick, or ſubtely, ſecular intereſt, or conjectures, for the Pillars of the Temple, to ſupport their Faith; and ſo upon the ſcore of Edification, break the Peace and Unity of the Church, and Obedience to our Governours, the great things of Religion.</item>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:95169:11"/>
                  <item> 3. In taking ſudden heats and warmth for true Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, when melting tones, affectionate expreſſions, ſolemn looks and behaviour, paſſion and vehemency, and other Arts have play'd upon the fancy, and put their conſtitutions into different motions, ſome have thought themſelves ſo ſtrangely Edifi'd, as though it was the impulſe and powerful acting of the Divine Spirit; which many times is no more than a bright or a lowring day can do, acting upon the Animal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and a Doſe of Phyſick will do the ſame. And if they carry the men no further, improve no virtue in them, they are nothing elſe but down right fleſh and blood. And they are hot and cold, high and low very changeable and uncertain, according as the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours flow, and as is the bodily temper of the men. Upon this account ſome are melted into Tears, and others are fired into Rage and Zeal, their Spirits, like Tinder, eaſily catching the flame; and theſe have ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in the worſt of Men, ſerving only the Deſigns of Fury and Hypocriſie, and can no more be called Edification, than the Fire from the Altar, that may conſume the Temple, Zeal. Yet ſuch miſtakes as theſe have been too common; Anger and Revenge have been called Zeal for God; Trade and Intereſt have been baptized Chriſtianity; Fury and Fumes of the Stomach have been thought the Divine Spirit; ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Looks and unmanly Poſtures have been fanci'd true Acts of Devotion, and when they themſelves were pleas'd, and in the good humour, God was reconcil'd, and when they were dull and heavy, the Spirit was withdrawn: and according as theſe heats and bodity paſſions were ſtirr'd, <note place="margin">Matth. 6.16.</note> ſo the Miniſtry was Edifying or unprofitable; pale Cheeks and hollow Looks have been
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95169:11"/>counted ſigns of Grace, and the Diſeaſe of their body paſs'd for the Virtue of their mind. And when a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine hath been ſo inſinuated, as to hit and favour theſe, they were ſtrangely improv'd, and had obtain'd a good degree in Religion. Many of theſe may be beginnings, or occaſions, leading unto Religion, and may ſerve ſome good purpoſes in men that can manage them well, but to cry up theſe for Edification, and going on unto prefection, is to betrary their People into the power of every Cheat and Impoſtor, who hath the knack to raiſe theſe heats, which paſs for reaſon and conviction of mind; and moſt commonly are great hindrances to ſolid and ſound reaſoning, plain diſcourſes, the true way to Edification, to make firm and laſting impreſſions upon the mind; while the filly and the weak, who are moſt ſubject to theſe heats and colds, the uncertain motions of their ſpirits, are fickle and inconſtant, turning round in all Religions, ſuch men being all ſail are more eaſily toſt about with every wind of Doctrine.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Argument to confirm the Anſwer is; That pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of better Edification will cauſe endleſs Diviſions in the Church. This Queſtion doth ſuppoſe that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man muſt judge, and ſo great a part of the World being ignorant and vicious, partial and prejudic'd, falſe, and inſincere to themſelves and others, they may run from Teacher to Teacher, from <hi>Presbyterian</hi> to <hi>Independent,</hi> from <hi>Independent</hi> to <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> or <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> and never ſtop till they come at their Grave to find out better Edification, <hi>ever learning,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>and never coming to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> ever ſeeking and never ſatisfi'd, till they find the Pattern upon the Mount, or the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> be come down from
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95169:12"/>above, till they meet with ſuch a prefect Church, as perhaps will never be here upon earth, till her great Maſter comes. The ignorant will eaſily miſtake, and who can know the heart and intention of the falſe and the hypocrite? And the Governour hath nothing to do here to retrench this liberty, which, as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, is either born with them, or given them by God. At this rate, may not every ſingle perſon be a Church, leaving all other Chriſtian Societies, fancying that he can better Edifie at home with the workings of his own mind, and ſome pretended infuſions of the Spirit, that he ſhall better meet with in his privacies and retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments than in an external and carnal Miniſtry and Crowd. When once they have torn the Unity of the Church in pieces, and ſet up their more Edifying Meetings, in comes whole ſhoals of Vices, Envy and Detraction, Strife and Emulation, Murmurings and Complainings, Fierceneſs and Wrath, and a great number of things more, prejudicial to the ſtate of the Kingdom, the intereſt of Families, the good of Friendſhip and all civil Converſation, a wonderful Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, deſtroying the very ſoul of Chriſtianity. The ſame Principles that divide them from this Church, will crumble them into endleſs Parties, and every little Chip may call it ſelf a Building, and ſo deſtroy all good Government and Diſcipline, ſo neceſſary to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate and preſerve Chriſtianity in the World. And ſhould I live to ſee that fatal day, when the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in our Church ſhould be diſſolv'd, and liberty given to every man, upon pretence of better Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to chuſe his Paſtour and his Church, ſo many Miſchiefs and Confuſions, would follow from it, that If there was any regard to common Chriſtianity, or ſenſe of temporal happineſs left within their Breaſt,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95169:12"/>they would too late repent their Schiſm, (as once in a great degree many of them did) and beg upon their Knees, that the Pale of this Government in Church might be ſet up again, and they would receive it with all its pretended load of Impoſitions. This will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly follow from dividing from the Church, to the laughter of <hi>Rome,</hi> and joy of all the Enemies of our Chriſtian Religion. All this would be avoided if men were ſenſible of the hainous nature of Schiſm, which the Apoſtles and all the ancient Chriſtians have painted forth in ſuch black colours, though others think our Diviſions in the Church are no more, than variety of Companies and Liveries in a City.</p>
            <p n="4">4. What great diſcouragement this is to an honeſt and truly Chriſtian Miniſtry. When a Paſtour of our Church ſhall diligently and faithfully, plainly and devoutly unfold the Articles of Faith, and lay down Rules for Practice, which will certainly bring him to Heaven, yet his Flock or Charge, one after another, upon pretence of greener Paſtures, greater Knowledge, better Elocution, Delivery, Tone, or the like, to be had elſewhere, ſhall run from him; will it not cool his Zeal, check his Labours, and affront his Perſon and Office? This may be done to the painful, as well as idle, to the judicious and learned, as well as impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and ignorant Paſtour, where the People ſhall have liberty of Separation for the ſake of Edification. The ill effects of this have turn'd upon their own Miniſters, and new Government, and the moſt own Miniſters, and new Government, and the moſt judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clous among them have ſadly complain'd of it. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly they Petition'd, for a painful and preaching Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, but this pretence of better Edification gives denial to their own requeſt; ſuch Diſcouragements as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95169:13"/>theſe happening ſeverely ſometimes to the beſt of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, as well as the worſt. And they have no cure for this, having put a power into the Peoples hands which they cannot recall; for neither King, Parliament, Biſhop, or Paſtour, can tell them what is Edification ſo well as themſelves. And are the Paſtours of the Church to be ſo treated and triſled with, who derive their Offices and Authority from God to Command and Perſwade, to Rebuke and Exhort, and have the Charge of Souls committed to them, for fancies, peeviſhneſs and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, to be ſcorn'd and diſcountenanc'd, and have their Miniſtry rendred uſeleſs, and the Sheep to govern the Shepherd; But what if our Paſtour be idle or remiſs in his Duty, or corrupt in his Faith, and teacheth Errour inſtead of ſound Doctrine, and we have no means of Edification? what muſt we do? muſt we take in Poyſon for Food? or not be ſed at all? to be ſure you muſt not run into Schiſmatical Separation; 'tis more tolerable to go to other Congregations of our Communion, that may be irregular, but 'tis not ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical; but thanks be to God we have a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which upon a juſt and modeſt Complaint, will quicken the lazy and negligent, correct the Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Paſtour, and reſtore to you true Edification.</p>
            <p>That this Diſcourſe may prevail upon ſuch who make this Queſtion, I deſire to recommend theſe two following things, which are very reaſonable, to their conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That if they fancy any Defects in our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they ſhould not hence conclude, that they have not ſufficient Edification in the Church to ſave their Sould. If upon a nice ſearch and critical enquiry, they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95169:13"/>think they have found ſome little Flaws and Defects, improper Phraſes, doubtful Senſes, and ſome ſmall Omiſſions in the matter of our Prayers and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, yet let them not conclude, that theſe can weigh in the ballance againſt the black ſin of Schiſm and Separation, and all its ſad Conſequences, which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd by nothing elſe but terms of communion plainly ſinful. Have not Divine Services been accepted, which were leſs perfect, and came not up to their rule? as is plain in <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s Paſſover, which was not to the <hi>Purification of the Sanctuary,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 30.18, 19, 20.</note> yet the good King's Prayer and <hi>the neceſſity</hi> of the time prevail'd with God <hi>to heal the People,</hi> that is, to repute them clean and well prepar'd, and their Sacrifice and Devotion good. Is there no Reverence to be paid to the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Authors of our Service and Reformation, but to tell them, they muſt divide from them, were they now living? for they cannot Edifie under that Religion and Government for which they dy'd. Is there, or will there over be any Government in the Church, ſo well fram'd and built, but ſome cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Surveyor can ſpy out ſome diſproportion or ill ſhape, eſpecially if aſſiſted by ill Nature, Emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, the Spirit of Pride and Contention, which is ever quick ſighted abroad, and blind at home? the difficulty of knowing what is utmoſt perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and abſolute purity of Adminiſtrations, (which, till attain'd, theſe Men think they are not to reſt in any Church) ſhould make them judge candidly, interpret fairly, and comply with every thing, that is not ſinful, to preſerve Peace and Love. When Men in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church are plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taught to believe well, to live well, and to dye well, and have good and proper Offices to ſerve
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95169:14"/>theſe great purpoſes, in order to their Salvation, what can they deſire more? to be better, or more ſav'd, we know not what it means. To leave ſuch a Communion, upon ſuch an account, proceeds from peeviſhneſs, uncharitableneſs, or ſome ill Principle, and is down right Schiſm, if ever there was Schiſm in the World. Bring but an honeſt, ſincere and teachable mind, and it will find improvement and advantage in Offices and Adminiſtrations fuller of ſpots and blemiſhes far than they can pretend to find in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church; but if the mind be by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by a Party, or corrupted by Deſigns, if is Pallate be vitiated, the beſt Food is courſe and inſipid to it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let Edification be plac'd in the ſubſtantial things of Religion. Some revolt from our Church for things wherein the Paſtour is ſolely concern'd, and others for things of decency, and indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; but theſe things do not concern the Caſe of Edification: That a right Faith, and an honeſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, are not taught in our Church, is only a ſcandal caſt upon her, to plead for their unjuſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration. For after ſhe hath plainly and diſtinctly taught the Articles of Faith, (as was prov'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) with the ſame Spirit and Zeal ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and preſſes Juſtice, Humility, Mercy, and every Virtue that is neceſſary to a true Chriſtian Life, and both under the Penalty of Eternal Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; theſe, and theſe alone, do truly Edifie the Souls of Men, as is plain, if we conſider, that our Prayers and Sacraments, our Churches Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and Diſcipline, and all other parts in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion are in order to, and miniſter unto Faith their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95169:14"/>head, that works by love: and the nearer theſe approach unto, and the greater ſervice they do to this deſign, the greater degree they have in Religion, and more value is ſet upon them. This is that Religion which our firſt Parent was of in his Paradiſe and innocency; <hi>Noah</hi> and his Poſterity in their Precepts, and Pious Men in different Countries before the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> thus ſerv'd God. And the ſcope and aim of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law, with its Temple and Utenſils, its Figures and Ceremonies, was to diſcipline and teach Men thus to be good, with allowance to the Nature of that People, and the Times they liv'd in. And the beſt and moſt knowing <hi>Pagans</hi> thought ſuch a Religion as this would moſt pleaſe God, who therefore in ſome meaſure did accept it, and reward it with greater Diſcoveries, as is plain in <hi>Cornelius,</hi> the Queen of <hi>Candaces</hi> Treaſurer, <note place="margin">Acts 8.27.</note> and others, who having not the Law, <note place="margin">Acts 10.4.</note> were a Law unto themſelves. In ſuch things as theſe the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of our Meſſias was to conſiſt, <note place="margin">Rom. 14.17.</note> not in Meat and Drink, but Righteouſneſs and Peace and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt. Such a Religion as this Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies in ſo great a degree, that 'tis the only Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Qualification for the upper World; where (though other great Parts of Religion ſhall dye with us) Righteouſneſs, Gratitude, Love of God, and glorifi'd Beings, and ſuch like Virtues, are of an Eternal Nature, ſhall be Ingredients of our Happineſs, and ſhall live with us for ever. What can be juſtly requir'd in Religion, to improve Mens Souls, that is not found in this? Is it to recover the Nature of Man now defac'd? Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95169:15"/>and Goodneſs, proceeding from Faith, their root, will make us truly good. Is it to give us a clearer Knowledge and worthy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of God? ſuch a practical Religion as this beſt prepares for greater knowledge, and in Scripture ſenſe is knowing of him. <note place="margin">1 John 2.4.</note> Is it Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to love God? the love of God conſiſts in obedience to his Precepts, ſubmiſſion to his Will, and reſignation to his Providence, otherwiſe 'tis flattery and fondneſs. Is it the deſign of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to bleſs Mankind here, and edifie them in their different relation? ſuch a Religion as this in our Church will do all that, and make the World a Paradiſe once more. This will give us the beſt character to judge by, whether we ſhall be ſav'd or no, being the perfection of all other marks and ſigns of our aſſurance of Life and Glory. When we are ſo Edifi'd and Religious, we are certain, that we are juſtifi'd and adopted, accepted and treated like the Sons of God, that we are in Chriſt, and have our wedding Garments on, our proper qualifications for the ſtate of Heaven. Such an honeſt Principle as this, makes our Prayers to be heard, our Devotions to be regarded, our Hopes to be ſtrengthened. This is the great intention of Chriſtianity, the Holy of Holys of our Temple, and all Religion. Such a Religion as this being ſo ſtrongly enjoyn'd and zealouſly taught in our Church, no ways diſguis'd by a dreſs of Phraſes, or corrupted into ſoft and luſhious fences, we need not complain for want of the means of Grace and Edification; we need not croſs the Seas, or run into private corners for it, 'tis nigh us,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95169:15"/>even at our doors, in the eſtabliſh'd Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Some uſe to ſay, that brown Bread and the Goſpel was very good Fare; but now they are grown as nice and delicate about Religion and Edification, as about Sawces and Dreſſes. Thanks be to God, 'tis a knowing Age, I wiſh it was as good. The Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of it doth not ariſe for want of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Information; if it doth, the Cure is near, let them value that Church and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that hath all things in it ſufficient to Mens Salvation. Let them not think ſo light of Schiſm. and ſpeaking evil of the Rule and Diſcipline in our Church, ſo fit and neceſſary to the preſervation of Chriſtianity; let them not cry up other <hi>Pauls</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollos</hi>'s; any other Teachers making Diviſions among us than this Church hath allowed for their Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, which is ſo far from Spiritual Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that it calls ſuch Men <hi>Carnal.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.4.</note> For the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of any other Nouriſhment, <hi>beſide ſuch</hi> plain Food, is Spiritual <hi>Pride and Wantonneſs,</hi> and they pamper their Fancies, while they ſtarve their Judgment. Let us therefore ſtick to ſuch a manly Religion, one great part of which is, to preſerve Obedience, Peace, and Order, and ſay of our Church, that teacheth it, as the Diſciples of its Author; <hi>Thou art he, and we ſeek for no other: whither ſhall we go, thou haſt the Words of Eternal Life?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>She hath all things in her that are neceſſary for the perfecting of the Saints, for the Work of the Miniſtry, for the Edifying of the Body, till we all come in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Faith, and of the Knowledge of the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95169:16"/>Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature, of the fulneſs of Chriſt.</hi> That ſuch a Religion as this in our Church is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing both to God and Man, we have the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of an Apoſtle: <note place="margin">Rom. 14.18.</note> 
               <hi>He that in theſe things ſerveth Chriſt, is acceptable to God, and approv'd of Men.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
